> > Jem Young: 所以让我们给它拍一个镜头。
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: So let's give it a shot.
我们不会做太多的但是记住或理解
We're not gonna do too much yet,
but memorize or understand how
要执行这些命令，例如，如何输入，如何编辑，如何保存和退出。
to do these commands like how to type,
how to edit, how to save and quit.
因为我们整天都在用它们
Because we will be using
them pretty much all day.
听起来很吓人
It sounds intimidating.
不会好的我们会慢慢来的
It won't be well, we'll go really slow.
>> Jem Young: 因此，为了救火，你可以输入 vi，
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: So to fire up vim,
you can type in vi,
这个人的页面就是要告诉你我们在做什么
the man pages again just to
show you that what we're doing.
我不喜欢给你命令你也不明白为什么
I don't like to give you commands and
you don't understand why.
所以我现在就做，明白了，我会在 vi里输入。
So I'll just do it now,
clear, and I'll type in vi.
>> Jem Young: 没有任何内容。
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: Nothing to it.
现在我们在一个文本编辑器中。
Now we're in a text editor.
让我们说我想做点什么
Let's say I wanna type something.
所以现在我处于指挥模式所以我只能说我
So right now I'm in command mode so
I can just say i, and
在下面的屏幕上我们看到插入意味着我们处于插入模式
at the bottom screen here we see insert,
means we're in insert mode.
您好，要摆脱插入方式，请点击 Escape。
Hello, and to get out of insert mode,
hit Escape.
现在我不再处于插入模式了对吧
And now I'm no longer in insert mode,
right?
我们已经有这么多了
We've got this so far.
直到你开始玩弄它
It's intimidating until you
start playing around with it.
因此，要进入最后一行方式，我将按下 Shift+冒号。
So to get into last line mode,
I'm gonna hit Shift+colon.
看底部屏幕有个冒号
See there's a colon here
at the bottom screen.
要退出我可以说 q但它不会让我
And to quit, I can say q,
but it's not gonna let me,
所以 Q bang 如果我想改写，但我还没有放弃。
thus the Q bang if I wanna override,
but I don't quit yet.
说我想保存这个文件，就像一件事，我不知道。
Let's say I want to save this file,
as, something, I don't know.
所以我可以说， wq，我没有给它一个文件名，我也不会说出这个名字。
So I can say wq, I didn't give it a file
name, and I'm not gonna name this one.
所以我就说不干了
So I'm just gonna say q quit.
>> Jem Young: 所有人都能进入并离开吗 ?
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: Did everybody
managed to get in and get out?
那就是，大概 90% 的是插什么的，
That's, [LAUGH] probably 90% of it is
just getting in inserting something and
出来了
getting out.
如果我想创造一个文件名
If I wanna create a filename, actually,
我想下次练习时我们会做的
I think we'll do it on the next exercise,
yeah.
所以，让我们创建一个文件。
So let's create a file.
我可以说， vi 呼叫 temp.
I could say, vi call temp.
>> Jem Young: 现在我在新文件里，我说，进入插入模式，
&gt;&gt; Jem Young: So now I'm in the new file,
I'll say, go into insert mode,
大家打个招呼
say hello, everyone.
感叹号和写 quit wq。
Exclamation points and
to write quit say wq.
它意味着写和退出。
It means write and quit.
如果我想保存我的写作，就不能打开文件来写作，什么?
If I just wanna save I hit write,
can't open file for writing, what?
wq ，试一下，不知道为啥不给我写。
wq, try that, I don't know why
it's not letting me write.
我知道原因
I know why.
这样我们就能学到教训
This we are gonna learn
a lesson in permissions.
所以现在我在根目录下所以我要去做正切的
So right now I'm in root directory,
so I'm going on a tangent, and
你不能把东西写在根目录里，它就不会让你了。
you can't write things in root directory,
it just won't let you.
所以我要做的就是用 cd~
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna cd~ and
what this means is it's
仅更改目录，而这只是 home的快捷方式。
just change directory and
this is just shortcut for home.
所以现在如果我做了 pwd，我就在我的主目录里，现在我可以自由地写文件了。
So now if I do pwd, I'm in my home
directory, now I can write files freely.
几乎没有几乎没有操作系统能让你以 root用户的方式写作
Almost, actually not almost, no operating
system is gonna let you write in root,
在根目录中只会有个坏主意
in the root directory,
just cuz it's a bad idea.
你不想在这里捣乱这就是你电脑的基础
[LAUGH] You don't wanna mess in here cuz
this is the base of your computer and
如果你开始写那些左右的文件不好的想法
if you start writing files left and
right, bad idea.
所以我们总是想确保我们只是在家里
So always we wanna make sure we're
just in our home directory or
一些工作目录。
some working directory.
我们可以看到我们在名录里
And ls, we can see we're in our directory.
现在我的 temp
So now, vi temp, and
大家好 !
now I can write Hello everyone!
如果我想看看就好了
And w quits, save,
if I wanna take a look at that,
我可以说猫 temp 什么都没有
I can say cat temp, nothing to it.
我可以用更少的温度，大家好 !
I can use less temp, Hello everyone!
没有什么要看的， q 退出。
Nothing to see, q to quit.
好了，每个人都在编辑一个文件，保存它吗 ?
All right, everybody in, out,
edited a file, saved it?
太好了我们晚点再做
Cool, we'll be doing more of that later.
所以我不想花太多时间在这里
So I don't wanna spend
too much time on it.
但你可能会被困住你会被困住
But you will get stuck probably and you're
gonna get stuck with bad permissions or
就像这样
something like that.
请告诉我，如果您执行或引用幻灯片，并确保您在
Just let me know if you do or reference
back the slides and make sure when you
请将文件写入正确的目录，并具有正确的许可权。
write a file, you're in the right
directory with the right permissions.
那就是病毒蛇了
So that was vim.
我只是花了很多时间
I just spent a lot more time on it.
但后来我意识到，你不是由我来告诉你的。
But then I realized,
you learn by doing not by me telling you.